#### **Alex Gillam**

8611 Hiawatha Rd.
Kansas City, Missouri 64114
(785) 760-0151
gillam96@gmail.com

#### **SUMMARY:**

Highly motivated data engineer with +10 years of overall experience and 6+ years of experience in the financial industry. I have been mostly focused on business intelligence and master data management up to this point. I'm extremely passionate about learning tools and technologies and am eager to take that next step in continuing my journey as a data professional.

#### **EDUCATION:**

University of Kansas – Lawrence, Kansas

(Aug. 2008- May 2013)

• Bachelor of Science in Information Systems

Asian School of Business - Thiruvananthapuram, India

(Dec. 2012 – Jan 2013)

University of Washington - Online

(Jan. 2017 - Aug. 2017)

SQL Server Development Certification
 (Data Modeling, Reporting, Integration, and Analysis Services)

#### **SKILLS/TOOLS:**

- RDBMS (MSSQL, Oracle, DB2) 9+ years
- MDM (Markit EDM) 7+ years
- SSIS/SSRS/SSAS 4+ years
- PowerBI 4+ years
- AWS 4+ years
- Scripting (Powershell, Batch, Shell) 6+ years
- Python 3+ years
- Streaming/Queuing (Apache Kafka, SNS/SQS, TIBCO EMS) 6+ years
- Data Diagramming tools (Lucidchart, Visio) 4+ years
- Scheduling/Orchastration (UC4) 6+ years
- Version Control (Github) 4+ years
- CICD (TeamCity, Octopus Deploy, Github Actions) 3+ years
- Infrastructure as Code (Terraform) 3+ years

## **EXPERIENCE:**

LPL Financial, Senior Data Engineer – Fort Mill, South Carolina (Remote) (May 2023 – Present)

- Design, develop and maintain data management systems for Team according to best practices and architectural guidance.
- Enhance/Maintain/support existing applications.
- Collaborate with other developers in designing.
- Collaborate with business partners, Architects, Quality Assurance, Release Management, and the Change Control board to plan, design, develop and implement solutions based on the needs.

- Suggest new processes and document reoccurring processes that will help streamline software development.
- Participate in all phases of the software engineering life cycle.
- Ensure the necessary platform technical documentation is maintained in an appropriate manner.
- Provide technical troubleshooting and advanced debug support.
- Create and implement an AWS cross-account data flow to provide the alerts required to retrieve business data from Snowflake.

# American Century Investments, Data Engineering Senior Specialist – Kansas City, Missouri (Jan. 2022 – May 2023)

- Act as team lead for MarkitEDM software version upgrades.
- Adhere to the IT department policies, procedures, and development practices, including application life cycle standards and procedures.
- Communicate effectively with business and technical teams.
- Act as deploy manager for releasing MarkitEDM code to production.
- Write batch files to automate deployment of MarkitEDM code and execute MarkitEDM solutions.
- Build a dynamic reusable data ingestion pipeline utilizing MarkitEDM, SNS/SQS, and MuleSoft to easily retrieve data lake data needed for security, price, and product/portfolio mastering.
- Assist Product Owner with writing technical stories based on business requirements in Digital.ai.
- Maintain data transformation scripts written in Python used to format csv files sent to an enterprise data lake containing master data.
- Responsible for discovering ways to combine active directory user roles and groups during a merging of our portfolio master instance with security master instance.
- Manage, configure, and host MarkitEDM Web UIs using IIS.
- Create CloudFormation templates to create AWS resources needed to support a MarkitEDM data mastery environment such as IAM users/roles, EC2 and RDS instances, S3 buckets, and CodeDeploy applications.
- Act as team lead for moving on-premise MarkitEDM applications to the cloud.
- Auto-install the MarkitEDM application and dependencies using Powershell scrips with AWS CodeDeploy and S3 to ensure best practices for disaster recovery.
- Mentor junior developers as well as train new team members.
- Partake in team code reviews.
- Review supporting documentation on a regular basis to ensure it is up-to-date.

## American Century Investments, Data Engineering Specialist – Kansas City, Missouri (May 2018 – Jan. 2022)

- Work closely with Investment Operations team that specializes in data management and governance.
- Build and maintain data pipelines used to master raw vendor data and distribute to downstream investment management systems (DB2, Oracle).
- Build out data reconciliation processes.
- Involved in requirements gathering, technical design, application development and architecture, validation testing, and maintenance of investment management applications.
- Write complex stored procedures for table pruning/housekeeping based on data retention policies set by business partners.
- Support day trading process by mastering securities with vendor data and distributing on-demand.
- Develop both backend MarkitEDM and UI solutions based on business requirements.
- Provide on-call support and troubleshoot issues if required.
- Build software scheduling and orchestration objects using UC4 (Automic).
- Match security data across multiple sources using MarkitEDM Data Matcher.

- Unit test MarkitEDM development in a development environment and parallel test in a TEST and QA environment and document test results through Digital.ai.
- Load raw data in various formats including CSV, XML, JSON.
- Publish master data using a variety of tools such as TIBCO EMS, Kafka, Oracle.
- Perform SQL tuning enhancements by reviewing and updating SQL queries used in MarkitEDM as well as creating indexes when appropriate.

## Corbion, Data Analyst – Lenexa, Kansas

(Mar.

## 2014 - May 2018)

- Responsible for ensuring all contracts and quotes in ERP system are accurately maintained on a weekly/monthly basis.
- Build and maintain SSRS reports for buyers to use to perform raw material cost analysis and demand forecasting.
- Develop critical market reports with input from buyers and category managers.
- Perform judgmental and cost reporting.
- Utilize SSIS to map data form flat files and a variety of sources.
- Created own Views utilizing SQL in order to pull data for various Corbion reports.
- Assisted with Data Mapping from Excel Spreadsheets into tables within the SQL Database.
- Translate analysis/reporting into business opportunities (finding opportunities for synergies between operating companies; reduce number of SKU's and or suppliers).
- Utilize SSRS for data analysis of pricing models.
- Create and maintain dashboards using Power BI and Tableau for spend visibility and spend control targets to measure KPIs.
- Maintain, analyze and reconcile procurement budget against business operating systems in order to get detailed understanding of the impact of price fluctuations throughout North America.
- Calculate the financial impact of certain changes on an ad-hoc basis if required.
- Utilize SSAS (multidimensional and tabular) to analyzing bills of materials.
- Experience writing requirements for various internal Corbion projects.
- Budget and reporting delivery against plan (Provide business with budget and forecast information).
- Checks on data delivery for the CI purchasing application savings tracking system (responsible for data integrity and completeness).
- Customer satisfaction (support given to the Procurement team).
- Act as a project manager and evaluate/monitor project.
- Develop multiple SSRS and SSAS tools and reports from scratch for data mining, reporting, and analysis.
- Create custom views utilizing T-SQL for data extraction.